巴斯蒂
Bast...
时间紧迫
Time is running out.
请让我治好我哥的病
Please allow me to heal my brother of this illness,
我就再也不质疑你的存在
and I will never question your existence again.
他的心率快速下降 有什么进展
His heart rate is dropping fast. Where are we?
即将完成一个序列
We are finishing a sequence now.
葛里奥 给我控制台
Griot, give me the controls.
遵命 公主
As you wish, Princess.
信赖率多少
What is the confidence rate?
百分之二十五
25 percent.
得试另一种方法
We'll have to try another way.
帝查拉国王的心率
King t'challa's heart rate
降至每分钟31下
has fallen to 31 beats per minute.
公主 您应该陪在他身边
Princess, you should go be by his side.
我得思考 通通出去
I have to think. Everyone, get out.
滚出去
Get out!
可信率多少
What is the confidence rate?
百分之二十九点一
29.1 percent.
打印
Print it!
公主 我明白很紧急
Princess, I am aware of the urgency,
但我得提醒您
but I must warn you,
这种合成心型药草
this synthetic heart-shaped herb
产生预期效果的概率微乎其微
has a minimal chance of producing the desired effects.
我不管 一定要成功
I don't care! Has to work.
葛里奥
Griot.
是 公主
Yes, Princess?
我哥的心率多少
What's my brother's heart rate?
你哥
Your brother
去见祖先了
is with the ancestors.
不
No.
[外语]我们感谢帝查拉国王的赠礼
[外语]黑豹
[外语]吾儿
[外语]至圣先王巴圣加国王后裔
[外语]第一代黑豹
[外语]我们释放你
[外语]赞美祖先
帝查拉 帝查拉 帝查拉
T'challa, t'challa, t'challa
t'challa, t'challa, t'challa
帝查拉 帝查拉 帝查拉
T'challa, t'challa, t'challa
帝查拉
t'challa
对不起…
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
(一年后)
(瑞士日内瓦 联合国)
我十分荣幸
It is an honor for me...
邀请拉玛达王后陛下
To invite her majesty, queen ramonda,
卢蒙巴之女
daughter of lumumba,
瓦坎达王国元首
sovereign ruler of the kingdom of wakanda.
主席先生
Mr. Chairperson,
我相信我能代表全体会员国发言
I believe I speak for all the member states here...
我感到十分失望
when I say that I am deeply disappointed
瓦坎达无法信守承诺
in wakanda's failure
与全球共同努力
to stand by promises to participate in global efforts...
面对国际上的挑战
to tackle international challenges,
分享资源
to share resources,
与各国充分合作
and full cooperation
处理振金的问题
concerning vibranium.
[法语]法国收到情报指出
[法语]振金能用来制造大规模毁灭性武器
[法语]现有金属探测器无法侦测
[法语]威胁到全球安全及武器禁扩原则
现在请拉玛达王后陛下发言
I now give the floor to her majesty, queen ramonda.
我国政策始终不变
It has always been our policy
无论如何都不买卖振金
to never trade vibranium under any circumstance.
原因不在振金的危险性
Not because of the dangerous potential of vibranium,
而是你们的潜在危险性
but because of the dangerous potential of you.
(马利安松哥 瓦坎达交流中心)
[外语]看不到保全影像
[外语]立刻趴下
[外语]脸朝地面 快…
[外语]振金工具呢
[外语]谁有权限
各位在此一副文明有礼的模样
You perform civility here.
但我们知道
But we know
你们的领袖与军事单位窃窃私语
what you whisper in your halls of leadership and in your military facilities.
国王已死
The king is dead.
黑豹已亡
The black panther is gone.
他们失去了守护者
They have lost their protector.
我们进攻的时刻
Now is our time...
终于到了
to strike.
安妮卡 你的矛呢
Aneka, where is your spear?
苏睿拿这些给我试用
Shuri gave me these to try.
其实 我比较喜欢它们
You know, I like them better.
女祖先给我们矛
Our foremothers gave us the spear...
因为它精准 优雅
Because it is precise, elegant...
又致命
And deadly.
有我在就别想换
It will not change under my watch.
是 将军
Yes, general.
我就叫你别带来
I told you not to bring them.
昨晚我们又有一处交流中心遇袭
Last night there was another attack on one of our outreach facilities.
某会员国涉入的证据
Proof of the involvement of a member state
此时正上传到各位的移动设备
is being uploaded to your mobile devices as we speak.
至于攻击者的身份…
And as for the identity of the attackers...
[外语]跪下
[外语]不客气
我们对此入侵行动的仁慈回应
Let our gracious response to this incursion
是希望递出橄榄枝
be an olive branch.
若进一步觊觎我国资源
Further attempts on our resources
将被视为侵略行为
will be considered an act of aggression
面对更强烈的回应
and met with a much steeper response.
我们为国王驾崩哀悼
We mourn the loss of our king.
但千万别以为瓦坎达失去了
But do not think for a second that wakanda has lost her ability
保护资源的能力
to protect our resources.
我们明白有些国家不断努力
We are aware of the ongoing efforts by some
在瓦坎达境外寻找振金
to find vibranium outside of wakanda,
祝你们好运
and wish you the best of luck.
(大西洋)
这是625号直升机 请求准许降落
This is rotor 625 requesting clearance to land.
下面见
All right. Meet you down there.
好
Yeah.
我以为你退休了
I thought you retired!
本来我也这么想
I thought I had too.
他们说那机器找到振金的概率
They said that machine had a one in a billion chance
是十亿分之一
of finding vibranium.
更低
Oh, less than that.
下去了
Here we go.
舱压稳定 每平方寸负1磅
Cabin pressure is stable at negative one p-s-i.
深度800尺
At 800 feet,
经过温跃层
passing through thermocline.
我的维生系统正常
All my life supports in the green.
收到
Copy you.
我们触底了
We've touched down.
很好 萨拉札 你接近探勘点了
Perfect. So, Salazar, you are near the site right there.
对 很惊人
Yeah, it's astonishing.
钻头似乎接触到金属物质
The drill seemed to make contact with a metallic substance.
不管是什么 都很坚硬
Whatever it is, it's solid.
没见过钻头被破坏成这样
I've never seen a drill bit chewed up like this before.
太夸张了
I'll be.
海洋中的振金
Vibranium in the ocean.
我们把探测器搬走
Let's go ahead and get the detector out of there,
毕竟只有那一台
since it's the only one we've got.
前往振金侦测器
Heading towards the vibranium detector.
萨拉札 画面一片黑
Okay, Salazar, we just went dark.
对 钻机没电了
Yeah. The rig lost power.
收到 我来处理
Copy that. I'm gonna fix it up here.
那是什么
What the hell was that?
杰克森
Jackson,
你也看到了吧
tell me you're seeing this?
等等 萨拉札的心率
Hang on. Salazar's heart rate.
萨拉札 能给我画面吗
Hey, uh, Salazar, can you give me a visual?
是冥河水母
It's a phantom jellyfish.
我没看过这颜色的
I've never seen one this color.
(失去讯号)
紧急潜水小组待命
Emergency dive team, stand by.
萨拉札 我们失去杰克森的生命征象
Salazar, uh, we just lost Jackson's vitals.
你有看到他吗
Can you see him?
没有 他不见了
No. He's gone.
他不见了 是什么意思
Can you clarify? What do you mean by, "he's gone"?
萨拉札 听到了吗
Salazar, do you copy?
萨拉札
Salazar?
(失去讯号)
史密提 这里有状况
Smitty, we got a situation out here.
什么声音
What's that sound?
魏斯特 有看见声音来源吗
West, you got a visual on what's making that sound?
魏斯特 听到了吗
West, how copy, over?
魏斯特 有看到吗
West, you got a visual?
是某种声波攻击
It's some kind of Sonic attack.
史密提 耳塞
Hey, smitty, earplugs.
我们遭受攻击
We are under attack.
立刻派突击队过来
You need to send in a strike team immediately.
收到 求救…这是625号直升机
Copy. Mayday, mayday, this is rotor 625.
我们需要立即支援
We are requesting assistance immediately.
是瓦坎达人
It's the wakandans.
一定是
It has to be.
韩德森
Henderson.
史密提 我们快走
Smitty, we gotta go.
韩德森
Henderson!
快走
Let's go.
怎么回事
What's going on?
离开船缘
Get off the edge.
[外语]上
快走…
Go, go, go, go!
快走
Now! Go!
旋转 甩掉他们
Spin! Spin them off!
好 他们不见了
Okay. They're gone!
天啊
Oh, my god!
快离开
Just get us out.
没事了
We're good.
突击队在哪
Where is the strike team?
不是瓦坎达人 他们是蓝色的
It wasn't the wakandans. They... they were blue.
大家都死了
Everyone is dead...
靠 怎么回事
Shit. What is going on?
我们被往后拉
We're getting pulled backwards.
天啊
Oh, my god.
天啊 抓紧
Oh, god! Hang on!
瓦坎达国的拉玛达王后
Queen ramonda of the nation of wakanda
昨天在联合国发表撼动人心的演说
gave an electrifying speech at the UN yesterday,
该国军人则护送被俘虏的佣兵
while members of her military escorted captive mercenaries
进入联合国会场
onto the floor of the UN.
拉玛达王后复位
A year has passed since queen ramonda
担任瓦坎达元首已一年
was reinstated as ruler of wakanda
帝查拉国王去年因不明疾病骤逝
after king t'challa's sudden death from an undisclosed illness last year.
全球都在关注这个强大的小国
All eyes are on the tiny, powerful nation,
它近来日渐孤立…
as it finds itself increasingly isolated...
[外语]王后
接近河界
Approaching the river border.
我们回家了
We are home.
公主
Princess.
等一下 我在忙
Just a moment. I'm in the middle of something.
我了解 公主 不过…
I understand, Princess, however...
你干扰到我的思路
You're disrupting my train of thought.
苏睿
Shuri.
母后
Mother.
我是想通知您 王后驾到
I was trying to tell you. The queen is here.
- 谢谢 - 那玩意害我不安
- Thank you. - That thing unnerves me.
我想有一天人工智能会杀光我们
I think that one day artificial intelligence is going to kill us all.
我的人工智能不像电影演的
My ai isn't like the movies, mother.
它对我言听计从
It does exactly what I tell it to do.
是啊 孩子也一样就好了
Yeah, if only children were the same.
大家似乎都在努力工作
Everyone seems to be working diligently.
对 迅速紧急反应任务
Yes. Rapid emergency response task.
未来可能有…
There could be any number of
各种未知的威胁 他们在研拟对策
unknown threats on the horizon, and they're creating solutions.
这是什么
Oh, what is this?
给军队穿的外甲装
Exo suits for our army.
赋予使用者超人类力量 速度及耐力
It grants the user super-human strength, speed, and durability.
但一如往常 奥克耶有意见
But, as always, okoye had notes.
她有什么意见
What were her notes?
她不喜欢
She hates them.
重制心型药草呢
What about recreating the heart-shaped herb?
有任何进展吗
Have you made any progress on that?
抱歉 公主
Excuse me, Princess.
雅阿之女娜奇雅又想与您联系
Nakia, daughter of yaa, is trying to reach you again.
或许您应该…
Maybe you should...
或许你应该照我的指示
Maybe you should continue your calculations
继续计算
as I instructed.
遵命 公主
As you wish, Princess.
我们需要的不是药草 母后
We do not need the herb, mother.
我们需要新技术
We need new technology.
那黑豹呢
What of the black panther?
这个角色数世纪以来团结了我们国家
The mantle has unified our nation for centuries.
黑豹是古董了 母后
The black panther is a relic, mother.
我不是想用药草拯救黑豹
I wasn't trying to save the mantle with the herb,
我是想救我哥
I was trying to save my brother.
苏睿
Oh, shuri.
知道今天什么日子吗
Do you know what day it is?
星期二
Tuesday.
我是指日期 孩子
The date, child.
哥的祭日
Brother's passing.
一年前的今天
One year ago today.
你有什么安排吗
Have you planned anything?
有 请你载妈妈出去一趟
Yes. It involves you taking your mother for a drive.
- 现在 - 对
- Right now? - Right now.
你能把基莫由珠留在这里
And you can leave your kimoyo beads here.
- 母后 - 不
- Mother. - No, no.
我们去的地方用不上它们
You won't need them where we are going.
还有另外两颗 对
And the other two. Yes.
你得陪我一起沉思 静下心来
You need to sit here with me. And with yourself.
唯有如此才能疗愈
It is the only way you are going to heal
帝查拉之死带来的创伤
from the wound caused by t'challa's death.
我没事 母后
I'm fine, mother.
不必替我操心
You don't have to worry about me.
他走了 但我要往前走
He's gone, but I'm moving forward.
帝查拉死了 不代表他离开了
T'challa is dead, but that doesn't mean he is gone.
那场病带走了你哥
When that illness took your brother from us,
我得带领受伤的国家和受损的世界
I had to lead a wounded nation and a broken world.
但还是抽空到野外来
But I still took time in the bush.
一路漫步到发现水为止
I wandered until I found water.
我坐下来
And I sat.
然后进行一场…
Then I did this ritual
我即将做给你看的仪式
that I am about to show you now.
我发现你哥在微风中
I found your brother in the breeze,
温柔而坚定地推着我
pushing me gently, but firm.
他的手彷佛搭在我肩上
Like his hand on my shoulder.
花了一点时间
It took some time,
但他真的在场
but he was there.
他不在 母后
He wasn't there, mother.
你感受到的
The presence that you felt
只是你的幻想
was just a construct of your mind.
那样你才能感到一点安慰或喜悦
Brought on so you could feel some comfort orjoy.
如此而已
That's all.
当你想到你哥时
What construct does your mind create
心中想到什么
when you think of your brother?
它有给你安慰吗
Does it offer you comfort?
还是折磨
Or torment?
过来 孩子
Come, child.
你怎么拿到的
How did you get this?
重要吗
What does it matter?
这和你的仪式有关吗
What does this have to do with your ritual?
焚烧葬礼服装
Burning of the funeral garments
象征哀悼期结束
marks the end of the mourning period
与已离世的亲人
and the beginning of a new relationship
展开一段新的关系
with our loved ones that have passed on...
我不要 母后
I'm not doing this, mother.
如果我坐着
If I sit
想念哥太久
and think about my brother for too long,
我会烧的就不是这些衣服
it won't be these clothes I'll burn.
而是这个世界
It will be the world...
和其中的每个人
And everyone in it.
苏睿
Shuri...
有件事我必须告诉你
Shuri, there's something that I need to tell you
与你哥有关
about your brother.
母后 等等
Mother, wait!
你要做什么
What are you doing?
这最好不是仪式的一环
This better not be a part of your ritual.
不是
It isn't.
停 别过来
Stop! Right there!
你是谁 怎么进来的
Who are you? And how did you get in here?
这地方太棒了
This place is amazing.
空气好原始
The air is pristine.
水…
And the water...
我母亲说过这种地方的故事
My mother told stories about a place like this.
化外之地 人们永远不必离开
A protected land with people that never have to leave.
永远不必改变自己
That never have to change who they were.
你们向世人公开秘密的原因是什么
What reason do you have to reveal your secret to the world?
一样的话我不喜欢讲第二遍
I am not a woman who enjoys repeating herself.
你是谁
Who are you?
我有许多名字
I have many names.
族人叫我库库尔坎
My people call me k'UK'ulkan...
但敌人叫我纳摩
But my enemies call me namor.
美军在我国底下探测到振金
The American military detected vibranium under my nation's domain.
我已阻止他们开采
I was able to stop them from minin' it,
但需要瓦坎达协助才能防止旧事重演
but we need wakanda's help to prevent it from happenin' again.
他们利用一名美国科学家设计的机器
They use a machine designed by an American scientist.
只有这里才有振金
Vibranium only exists here.
在瓦坎达
In wakanda.
母后 他身上包覆着振金
Mother, he's covered in it.
你儿子向世人展现振金的威力
Your son exposed the power of vibranium to the world.
其他国家因而展开搜寻
In response, other nations have begun searching the planet for it.
他的决定连累了我们
His choice has compromised us.
瓦坎达能找到那名科学家 带来给我
I think wakanda could find the scientist and bring them to me?
瓦坎达协助解决我们的困境才公平
It is only fair that wakanda helps to resolve our dilemma.
不准你潜入我国 跟我说什么叫公平
You do not sneak into my country and tell me what is fair.
我的士兵比这里的叶子还多
I have more soldiers than this land has blades of grass.
而且实力惊人
And they have incomparable strength.
我不想在不同的情况下回来
I would hate to come back under different circumstances.
等你们找到那科学家 往这里面吹气
When you have the scientist, blow into this,
放在海洋里
place it in the ocean.
我随后就到
I'll be there shortly afterwards.
为了你们好
For your own sake,
别对瓦坎达以外的人提到我
don't mention anything about me to anyone outside of wakanda.
你有看到他脚踝上的翅膀吗
Did you see the wings on his ankles?
他是怎么做到的
How did he do that?
我们必须召开议会
We must convene the council.
天眼完全没监测到任何活动
Heaven scrapers had no evidence of any activity at all.
河界遭人突破了
Oh, the river border has been breached, huh?
如果我的士兵在场
If my soldiers were present,
那个"鱼人"
this "fish man"
此时就被捕了
would be bound before us as we speak.
如果你的肌肉脑大军在场
If your muscle brains were present,
他们还会在那边被自己的羽毛呛到
they would still be there choking on their fuzzy adornments.
你这个光头魔鬼…
You bald-headed demon...
两位放尊重点
Show some respect, you two.
尊重
Respect?
这些人应该感到惭愧
These men should be ashamed to show their faces!
注意你的口气 贾巴里人
Watch your tone, Jabari!
我刚刚说到
As I was saying,
空中监测画面没拍到他
there was no aerial surveillance footage of him.
雷达也没发现
And nothing on the radar as well.
所以他在水中游了一百公里
So, he swam underwater for 100 kilometers.
他并非独行侠 还声称指挥一支大军
He was not alone. And claims to command a massive army.
他要我们送上一名美国科学家
He wants us to deliver one American scientist?
让他动手杀了他
So he can kill them?
快去找
Do it.
我们以前不必面对拥有振金的敌人
We never had to face an enemy with access to vibranium before.
如今没有黑豹保护我们
And we have no black panther to protect us.
因为这睿智的议会容许齐尔蒙格登基
That is because this wise council allowed killmonger to take the throne
烧光珍贵的心型药草
and burn up all of your precious heart-shaped herb.
恩巴库 你建议我们怎么做
M'Baku, what would you have us do?
我们应该找到那个鱼人 杀了他
We should find the fish man and kill him.
如果现在照他的话做
If we do what he is asking for now,
如何防止他回来 得寸进尺
what is to stop him from coming back and asking for more?
平身
As you were.
是我想太多 还是它变丑了
Is it just me, or does this keep getting uglier?
你想太多
It's you.
- 有用吗 - 有用
- So, does it work? - Yes.
这玩意能侦测到变更过的振金频率
This thing can detect the altered frequency of vibranium
透过水 石头甚至重金属
through water, stones, even heavy metals.
设计者太厉害了
Whoever built this is brilliant.
过来看
Come, look.
有的是订制零件 有的则像…
Some are custom parts and others look like
回收场捡来的
they gathered it from a junkyard.
我还是难以相信
I am still struggling to believe
瓦坎达境外出现振金
that vibranium exists outside of wakanda.
或许陨石不只一颗
Perhaps there was more than one meteorite.
地表大部分是水 不难想象
Our planet is covered of mostly water, so it's reasonable
另外一颗落入海中
that the other one just landed there.
这改变了我们的所有认知
This changes everything that we know.
大山岗 所有的传说和寓言
The great mound. All of the legends and fables.
那些故事深深烙印在我心中
Those stories are seared in my mind.
烙印听起来好痛哦
That sounds very painful.
我们终究得找到这个科学家
So we have to find this scientist after all.
我有个想法
I do have an idea.
需要公主协助
I'm going to need the Princess.
免谈
Out of the question.
她根本不适合外出
She is in no state to be in the field.
[外语]王后
出门对她或许有好处
It may do her some good to get out.
那可能正是她需要的
It might just be exactly what she needs.
何况我闭眼睛都能执行这项美国任务
Besides, I can do this American operation with my eyes closed.
我担心的不是美国人
It's not the Americans that I'm worried about.
这个纳摩
This namor,
他轻易突破我们的边防
he snuck past our defenses.
那种事不会再发生
That will never happen again.
他并非一个人
He was not alone.
她有我在身边
She'll be with me.
所以…
So,
何时出发
when are we leavin'
我想见我最喜欢的殖民者
so I can see my favorite colonizer?
(美国维吉尼亚州)
拜托
Come on.
我懂了
Yeah, I got it.
I got it.
能慢一点吗
Will you slow down?
没先打个电话
You didn't think to call?
我哪有你的号码
Now, why would I have your number?
我们在找建造振金探测器的科学家
We are looking for the scientist who built the vibranium detector.
在大西洋里的是你们
So it was you guys in the Atlantic?
少来 开采船
Come on. Mining ship.
伤亡惨重
Lot of casualties.
发生什么事
What happened?
真假
Seriously?
那是联合行动 我们和海豹部队
It was a joint operation. Us and the seals.
他们30名菁英 我们2名优秀探员
Thirty of their top guys, two of our best officers,
我的朋友
friends of mine.
都死了
Gone.
就那样走了
Just like that.
因为他们在追踪振金…
You throw in the fact that they were tracking vibranium...
我保证瓦坎达与此事无关
I can assure you wakanda had nothing to do with this.
那是谁
So who was it?
天啊 我们原本应该…
God, look, the way that this is supposed to work
互通情报 有来有往
is that I give you information and you reciprocate.
为了安全起见 我们不能告诉你
For our own safety, we cannot tell you.
我们必须先找到那个科学家
It's imperative that we get to the scientist
以免又出事
before anything else happens.
你欠我一次 罗斯
You owe me, Ross.
你欠我哥
You owe my brother.
听着
Okay, look.
有些被判死刑的探员
There are agents who have been sentenced to death
泄漏的情报都没这么多
for less than I'm about to give you now.
我们来了新的局长
And we got a new director.
她紧盯着我
She's watching me like a hawk.
我们会非常非常小心
We will be very, very careful.
不只小心 动作要快
Not just careful, you gotta be fast.
美国需要另一台机器
The us needs another machine
全世界只有这小鬼
and this kid is the only person in the world
知道怎么建造
who knows how to build one.
他们会去找她
So they're comin' for her.
小鬼
A kid?
(马萨诸塞州州剑桥)
你忘了给我钱
You forgot to venmo me.
我忘了 八百对吧
Ah, it slipped my mind. It's eight hundred, right?
八百是昨天的价码 今天一千
Eight hundred was yesterday's price. It's a band today.
抢钱啊
That's predatory. I...
我做了整只机械手
I built the whole robotic hand.
你只修正了抓握算法
You just corrected the grip algorithm.
你拿到什么成绩
And what grade did you get?
谢谢
Thanks.
那是iPhone吗
Is that an iPhone I see?
很低阶
Primitive.
[外语]王后
我们找到那个科学家了
We have located the scientist.
她的学校跟瓦坎达乡村学校同等级
She is in the American equivalent of a wakandan village school.
学校
A school?
拜托跟我说她是教授
Please tell me it is a professor.
她是学生 母后
It's a student, mother.
不能把她交给纳摩
We can't give her to namor.
把这个学生带回瓦坎达
Bring this student back to wakanda.
[外语]是 王后
接下来让我来
I've got it from here.
等等 也许我该跟她谈一下
Wait. Maybe I should speak with her.
那样比较低调
It will be more discreet.
我可以很低调
I can be discreet.
怎样
What?
- 没事 - 化妆的关系吗
- Nothing. - Is it the makeup?
- 粉底颜色不对 - 颜色没错
- It's the wrong shade, isn't it? - It's the right shade.
Fenty 440 很好看
Fenty 440. You look good.
我能假装成学生混进去
I can blend in as a student.
我能搞定
I can do this.
- 给你五分钟 - 赞
- You get five minutes. - Yes!
(解题才敲门)
唉
Yo!
莉莉威廉斯
Riri Williams?
我不让人直接来 你得上网站
Yo, I don't do drop-bys no more. You gotta go to the website.
是一个加密档案
It's an encrypted file.
我想隔空投送
I wanted to airdrop it.
你…
You the...
你是苏睿公主
You're Princess shuri.
你怎么跑来这里
What the hell are you doing here?
靠 我要被征召了吗
Oh, shit, am I getting recruited?
我想问你为中情局做的振金探测器
I'm here about the vibranium detector that you built for the CIA.
我不是为中情局做 是为了冶金学课
I ain't built no detector for no CIA. I made that for my metallurgy class.
- 学校作业 - 对
- A school project? - Yeah.
教授说我绝对做不出来
My professor said I'd never be able to do it.
但我是年轻有才华的黑人 对吧
To be young, gifted, and black though, right?
你们在瓦坎达应该不会这么说
Y'all probably don't say that in wakanda.
你几岁
How old are you?
19岁
Nineteen.
长辈不见得能接受年轻有为
Brilliance at a young age is not always accepted by the elders.
你花了多少时间
How long did it take you?
几个月
Couple months.
- 几个月 - 最难的部分是…
- Couple months? - The hardest part was
找到够大的麦拉片来盖住…
finding big enough mylar sheets to cover the...
等等 我惹毛瓦坎达了吗
Wait, did I piss offwakanda?
不只我们
Not just us.
你在这里不安全了
This place is no longer safe for you.
收拾东西跟我走 快
Gather your things and come with me. Right now.
我15分钟后要上微分方程课
I got differential equations class in, like, 15 minutes.
好
Okay.
好啦
你在这里等
You wait right here.
我去上厕所 我…
I'm gonna go to the bathroom. I'm just gonna...
我已经搞定了
I had it under control.
我说五分钟 给了你六分钟
I said five minutes. I gave you six.
出去 滚出我宿舍
Get out. Get out of my dorm.
出去
Get out!
嘿
Hey.
我警告你们 别再过来一步
I'm warning you! Do not take another step toward me!
他们是怎么教孩子招待客人的
See how they teach the children to treat their guests? Mm!
你带矛进来
You brought a spear in here?
You brought a spear in here.
我喜欢她
I like her.
喂…放下
Hey, hey, hey, hey, hey.
Put it down, put it...
你会受伤的 别这样
You'll hurt yourself. Come on.
没关系 公主
It's all right, Princess.
小女生
Small, small girl.
我给你两个选择
I am going to give you two options.
你可以来瓦坎达…
You can come to wakanda,
以清醒或昏迷状态
conscious or unconscious.
你才得清醒一下 看看你的样子
You need to be conscious of the way that you look.
顶着一张灰灰的脸趴趴走
Walking round here, all that ash on your head.
- 好笑吗 - 不好笑
- Oh, it's funny? - No, it's not.
- 我就跟你说 - 很好看
- I told you! - You look good.
冷静点 我们离开
Calm down. We'll leave, okay?
她能单独对付那个脚踝有翅膀
And she can deal with that merman with the winged ankles
想杀她的人鱼
who wants to kill her all by herself.
- 你可以的 - 用你的暖炉
- You got this. - Mm, with your heater.
走了啦
Come on. Let's go.
什么
What?
这到底是什么地方
What exactly is this place?
我帮卫生局长修过卡车
I fixed a few trucks for the head of sanitation.
他就让我在这车库工作
He lets me work out of this garage in exchange.
我得拿工作用的笔电
I just have to grab my work laptop.
拜托什么都别碰
Please don't touch anything.
这你别担心
You don't have to worry about that.
看来不多 却是我毕生的心血
It may not look like much, but it's my life's work in here.
机器的设计在笔电里
So, the design for the machine is on that laptop?
对
Yeah.
你就放在车库的桌上
And you just leave it on a desk in a car garage?
我设了2065字节加密
I got 2065-byte encryption on that thing.
了不起 有害自己打不开过吗
That's impressive. Ever locked yourself out?
我花了整学期才解锁
Took me the whole semester to get back in.
为了破解自己的密码
Had to build a functional quantum computer
我还组了一台量子电脑
just to crack my own encryption.
你在建造什么 是史塔克科技吗
What is it you're building here? Is it stark tech?
我说什么都别碰
I said don't touch anything.
公主 美国执法人员抵达您的位置
Princess, American law enforcement has arrived at your location.
- 可恶 - 那是谁
- Shit. - Who was that?
我的人工智能
My ai.
他们要包围我们
They are surrounding us.
我以为你说有人鱼在追我
I thought you said a merman was after me.
那是联邦探员
That's the feds.
现在别来乱啦
Oh, I do not need this shit right now!
我本来好好的
I swear to god, I was doing so well!
准时上课 我真是蠢爆了
Goin' to class on time. I must be dumb as hell.
真蠢 我以为瓦坎达公主
Real dumb thinking that the Princess of wakanda
会出现在门口 现在却来了联邦探员
is gonna show up at my doorstep and then shit about to pop off.
我想我要冒险去找那个人鱼
I think that I'm actually gonna take my chances with this merman,
至少他没带联邦探员到我车库
because at least he never brought the FBI to my garage!
喂 纳摩击沉载满中情局特务的船
Hey. Namor sank an entire ship of CIA operatives...
这是联邦调查局 就因为你的机器
This is the federal bureau of in vestigation. Because of your little machine.
外面的执法人员…
So those popo out there...
是你最不必担心的
Are the very least of your worries.
我们得合作才能离开
Listen, we need to work together to get out of here.
将军 他们把我们包围了
General, they've got us surrounded.
或许我们该分开走
Maybe we should just split up.
不行
Out of the question.
这车子能动吗
Does this vehicle work?
这实验室一切都能用 包括这辆机车
Everything in this lab works. Including this bike.
想都别想 而且我们有三个人
Don't even think about it. Besides, there are three of us.
你们两个 我开这台
Two of y'all. I'm takin' this.
我就知道
I knew it.
别跟我说你两个月就做好了
Don't tell me that you built this in two months.
断断续续花了好多年
I spent years on this. On and off.
很好 你飞过它吗
Nice. Have you flown it yet?
那玩意能飞
That thing can fly?
有整个网络影音频道都是我的视频
There's an entire YouTube channel dedicated to sightings of me.
太厉害了
That's awesome.
- 我们有拘捕令 - 过来
- We have a warrant to detain... - Come.
要拘提学生莉莉威廉斯
The student riri Williams.
无线发射器
Wireless transmitter,
- 我们才能沟通 - 别想偷溜
- so we can communicate. - Don't try to scurry off.
奥克耶将军 苏睿公主
General okoye, Princess shuri,
手举高走出来
come out with your hands up.
一堆废物
What a hunk ofjunk.
喂 麻烦小心
Hey, please be careful.
- 你不会被捕 - 钥匙在座位上
- You will not be placed under arrest. - Keys are on the seat.
一旦过了桥
Once we get to the other side of the bridge,
就能在波士顿车阵中甩掉他们
we can lose them in Boston traffic.
将军 我们非分开不可
General, we really need to split up.
听好 这不是你的实验室 这是外面
Listen to me. We are not in your lab. We are in the field.
叫她上车
Now, get her in the car.
老爱吼我
Always shouting at me.
机动小组冲进入口 倒数三 二…
The tactical unit will breach the entrance in three, two,
一
one.
联邦调查局 别动
FBI! Don't move!
那是什么东西
What the hell is that?
靠 她有钢铁人装 撤退
Oh, shit! She got an iron man suit? Fall back!
停在原地
Stay where you are!
它果然能飞
Guess it can fly.
- 葛里奥 - 是 公主
- Griot! - Yes, Princess.
- 快 - 远端驾驶启动
- Now! - Remote piloting activated.
苏睿 不
Shuri! No!
冲啊
Let's go!
葛里奥
Griot.
给我画面
Give me a visual.
- 葛里奥 - 是 将军
- Griot... - Yes, general?
带我去找公主
Take me to the Princess
否则我的矛就插进你的中央处理器
or I will drive my spear so deep into your cpu,
你一千年都别想复活
you will not be able to process basic input for a millennia.
请稍候 将军
Just one moment, general.
奥克耶 我去找你
Okoye, I'm on my way to you.
葛里奥 快让我操控这辆车
griot, give me control of this vehicle right now!
我在帮你开路
I am clearing you a path.
交给你了 将军
She's all yours, general.
进行手动驾驶
Manual drive engaged.
我们得找个撤离点
we need to find an extraction point.
河对岸有一个
There's one across the river.
他们要封锁桥梁
hey, yo, they cuttin' off the bridge.
公主 有一架监视无人机锁定您
Princess, there is a surveillance drone locked onto you
多高
How high?
三万尺
Thirty-thousand feet.
等等
hang on.
看我的
I got it.
快啊 莉莉
Come on, riri.
你得找到微分方程
You gotta find these differential equations.
等相对速度拉平…
Once the relative velocity evens out...
莉莉 没有氧气罩
Riri, I'm not sure you can reach that drone
你恐怕追不上无人机
without an oxygen mask.
含氧量55%
Oxygen level is now 55%.
两万八千尺
Twenty-eight thousand feet.
含氧量30%
Oxygen level is now 30%.
最大加速 我只要调整欧拉角
Maximum acceleration. I just need to adjust my euler angles and that should...
应该能让它落在…
That should drop it right on the...
含氧量0%
Oxygen, 0%.
无人机不再追踪您
The drone is no longer tracking you.
高度五百尺 下降中
Altitude, 500 feet and falling.
莉莉 你还好吗
Riri! Are you okay?
- 莉莉 - 还好
- Riri! - Yea h.
我没事
I'm good.
- 来了 - 让开
- Incoming! - Get out of the way!
天啊
Incoming! Get out of the way!
- 可恶 - 别担心
- Shit! - And no worries.
我送特别快递来 倒数三…
I got a special delivery for y'all in three,
二 一
two, one...
漂亮 莉莉
Nice one, riri!
莉莉
Riri!
怎么回事 苏睿
What just happened? Shun!
苏睿
Shun!
公主生命征象稳定 将军
The Princess's vitals are stable, general.
稍后应该会恢复意识
She should regain consciousness momentarily.
再靠近一步…
Take another step closer
我就杀光你们
and iwill kill you all.
放下武器
Drop your weapons!
[外语]杀了科学家
[外语]我来对付目击者
[外语]好
她是蓝色的吗
Hey, is she blue?
[外语]先杀了这个女的
放下武器
Drop your weapon!
[外语]去找纳摩菈
[外语]杀鸡焉用牛刀
[外语]怎么这么久
[外语]现在不是闹着玩的时候
奥克耶
Okoye!
等等
Wait!
启动翻译
Activating interpretation.
我是苏睿
I'm shuri.
瓦坎达公主
Princess of wakanda.
我要你们带我去找纳摩
I demand that you take me to namor.
不要伤害这个女孩
Do not bring harm to this girl.
两人都活捉吗
Do we take them both alive?
对 阿杜玛
Yes, attuma.
呼吸
Breathe.
苏睿
Shun!
我是中情局的罗斯 有目击者吗
Ross, from the agency. You got any witnesses?
没有 我们认为是瓦坎达人
None. But we think it was the wakandans.
你说什么
Excuse me?
总部告知他们会来
Our field office got a tip from Langley
that they were coming.
是 谁打的电话
Right. Who made that call?
她
She did it.
德芳亭局长
Director de fontaine.
真假
Really?
呃…
Well...
探员认为是瓦坎达人
Uh, agent thinks it was the wakandans.
他们摧毁那艘船后 我们就紧迫盯人
Yeah, we've been on every one of them since they took out our ship.
所以我才要你来
That's why I wanted you here.
你挺帅的
You're lookin' good.
我尽量
Oh. Well, I try.
家里弄了健身室吗
You put that home gym in?
对 去年
Yeah. Last year.
说不定改天去你家踩飞轮
Maybe I'll drop by sometime and jump on your peloton.
你好
Howdy.
我是负责指挥的特别探员
I'm special agent in charge.
很好 要向我说明物证吗
Oh, good for you. You wanna walk me through the evidence here, or what?
- 是 你先请 - 好
- Yeah. Okay. - After you.
发生什么事
So, what happened here?
我们认为是车祸
Um, we think it was a car crash,
但是找不到车子
but we're having trouble finding the cars.
什么意思 发现时就这样
What do you mean? It was just like this when you found it?
对 应该有人移走车子
Yes. We think someone involved got rid of the vehicles.
怎么移走
Got rid of them how?
丢进河里
They dumped them into the river.
太扯了
You're kidding me.
上面有麻省理工学院贴纸
It's got an mit sticker on it.
立刻传给国安局
I want that transferred to the NSA immediately.
罗斯 你油箱满的吗
Hey, Ross? You got a full tank of gas?
能载我回总部吗
Can you give me a ride back to Langley?
车程八小时
It's an eight-hour drive.
对 我们能聊聊这案子
Yeah. We can talk about the case.
我不介意…
Actually, wouldn't mind...
为离婚前我说的几件事道歉
Apologizing to you for a couple of things I said during our marriage.
他们是蓝色的
They were blue.
他们具有超人类的能力
And they had superhuman strength.
骑着鲸鱼从水中冒出来
And they came from the water on the backs of whales.
我击倒三个 以为杀死他们
I struck down three of them with blows that should've killed them,
但他们又爬起来
but they Rose again.
我希望立刻出发 救回公主
I wish to leave immediately to retrieve our Princess.
奥克耶
Okoye,
你将被摘除瓦坎达军队将军的头衔
you will be stripped of your rank as general of wakanda's armies
以及朵拉亲卫队的地位
and your status as dora milaje.
[外语]请求发言
[外语]王后
说吧
You may.
[外语]我求您
我已付出一切
I have given everything.
让我为拯救国家及王位而死
Let me die saving my country and that throne.
[外语]我求您 王后
请容我将功赎罪
Allow me to make this right.
将功赎罪
"Make it right"?
我的女儿生死未卜
I do not know if my daughter is alive or dead.
或许我们操之过急了
Perhaps we are being too hasty.
为了瓦坎达 她拿着矛对抗丈夫
She raised a spear against her own husband for wakanda.
她的背骨丈夫如今仍在
Where is her treacherous husband now
她想看还是能去看他 而我的丈夫
but in a place where she can visit if she wished? Mine...
已经与祖先同在了
Is with the ancestors.
我是世界第一强国的王后
I am queen of the most powerful nation in the world,
全家人却都走了
and my entire family is gone!
我没有付出一切吗
Have I not given everything?
起来 将军
On your feet, general.
齐尔蒙格登基后
I stood by you
我依然大力支持你
after killmonger took the throne,
当我去请求贾巴里人保护时
and you and the elders in this room stood by him
你和在场的长老却支持他
while I ran begging to the Jabari for protection.
我警告你这次任务别带我女儿去
And I warned you about taking my daughter on this mission,
你却害她失踪
and you lost her.
所以今天
So, today,
我受够了
I am done.
你在吗 葛里奥
Are you here, griot?
是 王后
Yes, my queen.
苏睿被绑架时你在她身边吗
Were you with shuri when she was abducted?
是的
I was.
你能追踪她的基莫由珠吗
Are you able to track her kimoyo beads?
弹道监识组在剑桥各处发现子弹
Ballistics found slugs all over Cambridge.
那些瓦坎达人到处趴趴走
Those wakandans really took a tour of the city.
搞不懂他们怎么查出谁建造的
I can't see how they figured out who built it.
那是高度机密情报
That information is highly classified.
这什么
What is that?
- 新的铃声吗 - 可恶
- That's a new ringtone? - Oh, shit.
局长 抱歉 我得接一下
Uh, director, I'm sorry. I'm gonna have to take this.
别叫头衔 接吧 我无所谓
It's enough with the titles. Just take it. I don't care.
亲爱的甜心
Hey, honey sweetheart.
我跟我老板在一起
Uh, no, I'm... I'm with my boss. Now.
她要离开了
Actually, she's leaving.
好
All right.
我会在家工作 然后洗个澡
I'm gonna work from home, and then have a shower.
艾佛瑞特罗斯
Everett Ross.
拉玛达王后
Queen ramonda?
你拿苏睿的基莫由珠做什么
What are you doing with shuri's kimoyo beads?
我不知道是她的
I didn't know they were hers. All right?
我在一个惨烈的犯罪现场发现的
I just found them at a pretty ugly crime scene.
那个学生在你们手上吗
Do you have the student?
苏睿想救她 结果两人都遭挟持
Shuri was trying to save her when they were both taken.
什么 被谁挟持
What? Taken by who?
我局里认为是你们
My agency assumes it was you.
我担心他们可能知道
And I'm worried they might be onto the fact
我为苏睿和奥克耶指引方向
that I pointed shuri and okoye in the right direction.
如果她们有危险 我想帮忙
Look, if they're in danger, I wanna help.
但我得了解实情才行
But I can't if I don't know what's going on.
现在恐怕有一个新的世界强权
I am afraid there is a new world power at play.
我们已掌握的国家 还是别人
A country that's already on our radar? Or you mean someone else?
目前我只能说这么多
That is all I can say for now.
麻烦你
Please,
贵国政府若决定对怀疑之事采取行动
alert me if your government decides to act
请先告知我
on their suspicions.
没问题
Yeah. Sure.
如果我能帮什么忙 尽管说
Uh, look, if there's anything I can do to help, let me know.
我的命是苏睿救回来的
I owe shuri my life.
葛里奥 苏睿戴着耳环吗
Griot, did shuri have her earrings with her?
他们在北大西洋失去踪影
I lost track of them in the north Atlantic,
带走她的人说犹加敦马雅语
but the people who took her spoke yucatec Mayan.
(海地 海地角)
[外语]你好
[外语]你来找校长吗
[外语]她在那边
[外语]很好
[外语]你好
[外语]你们先离开一下
母后
Queen mother.
这里的一切都能让孩子学习
Everything is a lesson here for the children.
他们会粉刷墙壁 喂鱼
They painted the walls, they feed the fish,
种我们吃的所有食物
and they grow everything we eat here.
有些概念我并不陌生
I recognize some of the concepts here.
但你用了不同的素材
But you are using different material.
是 我们只用海地找得到的东西
Yes, we use strictly what we can find here in Haiti.
大家发现你没参加帝查拉的葬礼
You were missed at t'challa's funeral.
母后
Queen mother.
你离开我们六年了
It's been six years since you left us.
我以为你至少会回来参加葬礼
I thought you would at least come back for the ceremony.
我怕…
I was afraid
葬礼就代表他真的走了
of how final the funeral would be.
娜奇雅 雅阿之女
Nakia, daughter of yaa,
无论你去哪里 都是瓦坎达人
wherever you go, you are still wakandan,
你也知道死亡不是终点
and you know death is not the end.
[外语]谢谢
老家的乡亲还好吗
How is everyone at home?
苏睿遭挟持
Shuri has been taken.
什么
What?
你曾经渗透过许多国家
You have infiltrated many nations before.
[外语]那是很久以前的事了
当时我跟现在不一样
I was a different person then.
我需要有人查出她被关在哪里
I need someone who can find where she is being held,
营救她 暗中行动
and rescue her, without being seen.
谁会甘冒与瓦坎达开战的风险
Who on earth would risk war with wakanda?
天啊
Oh, my god.
呼吸…
Okay, breathe. Breathe.
别叫我呼吸
Oh, don't tell me to breathe.
我们到底在哪
Where the hell are we?
在洞穴里 我不确定是哪里
We're in a cave. I'm not sure where.
天啊
Oh, my god!
那是什么
What is that?
萤火虫 它们的幼虫会发光
Glow worms. Their larva gives off light.
先冷静
Just calm down.
有没有新的黑豹
Okay, is there, like, a new black panther
- 你能叫来接我们 - 没有
- that you can call to come and get us? - No...
为什么
Why not?
情况不同了
Because it doesn't work like that anymore.
黑豹走了
The black panther is gone.
我被绑架 你们却没黑豹了
So y'all stopped having black panthers when I get kidnapped?
[外语]公主
[外语]王室都穿传统服装
[外语]我们为您做好了
你听得懂吗
Do you understand her?
不完全懂
Not completely.
不行
Nuh-uh.
那衣服有诈
That is some supervillain shit right there.
电影都这样演
That's in every movie.
莉亚公主
Princess Leia.
《美女与野兽》的贝儿
Belle from beauty and the beast.
《印第安纳琼斯》那个白人女孩
That white chick from Indiana Jones.
没关系
It's fine.
你该看看我在战士瀑布穿什么
You should see what I have to wear at warrior falls.
[外语]跟我来
等等
Wait.
你不会把我丢在这里吧
You're not leaving me in here, are you?
我会回来
I'm coming back.
我马上回来
保持冷静
Stay calm.
[外语]吃吧
(墨西哥 犹加敦半岛)
[外语]太太你好 很高兴认识你
[外语]有什么事吗
[外语]我叫玛莉亚阿达娜 美里达来的学生
[外语]没兴趣 拜托你走开
[外语]没问题 我不想打扰你 听我说句话
[外语]我的教授提到一项研究
[外语]你告诉研究人员 你碰到一件事
[外语]一个难以想象的人
[外语]跟外地人讲话准没好事
[外语]我求你
[外语]快走开
[外语]我也碰过他
[外语]有时会在海边看见一个
[外语]脚上长翅膀的男人
[外语]我们以为他是幽灵
[外语]库库尔坎
[外语]我们的羽蛇神
[外语]统治着这里与底下的领域
[外语]我很想去那座海滩
[外语]但是要小心
[外语]库库尔坎在这里的时间比你我更久
[外语]那些心怀不轨
[外语]去找他的人
[外语]始终没有回来
[外语]迷失在深海里
[外语]永远消失
公主
Princess.
欢迎
Welcome.
请 别客气
Please, feel free.
好漂亮
This is beautiful.
那是我母亲的
That was my mother's.
这些都是中美洲文物
These are all mesoamerican artifacts.
应该来自16世纪
Most likely 16th century.
你从那时活到现在
Have you been alive since then?
你的母亲是人类
Your mother was human.
她是
She was.
后来她成了别的东西
Then she became something else.
- 怎么变 - 怎么变
- How? - "How?"
方法绝对不如原因重要
"How" is never as important as "why."
(犹加敦萨马 1571年)
西班牙征服者赶走我母亲和村民
My mother and her village were driven from their farms
强占农田 从另一个世界带来天花
by Spanish conquistadors who brought the smallpox,
一种可恨的语言 和教义
a hateful language, and dogma from another world.
面临饥荒
Facing starvation,
战争与疾病
war, and disease,
我的族人向恰克求助
my people turned to chaac...
我们的雨水与丰饶之神
Our god of rain and abundance.
恰克让我们巫师看到一个幻象
Chaac gave our shaman a vision...
拯救族人的方法
A way to save his people.
恰克带他到一株蓝岩中长出来的植物
Chaac led him to a plant sprouting from a blue rock.
我母亲当时腹中怀着我
My mother was pregnant with me at the time,
不肯吃下那种植物
and she did not want to ingest the plant
担心对我造成影响
for fear of what it may do to me.
[外语]不 我的宝宝
但巫师的说法令人信服
But the shaman was convincing.
[外语]你的宝宝生病了
[外语]只有这个能治好他
[外语]你的宝宝会第一个在我们新家出生
[外语]将这份礼物当成承诺
[外语]他将是我们的新国王
他们都病倒了
They all fell sick.
他们的生命
And their lives,
在那里的日子
their existence there,
就此结束
ended.
那种植物夺走他们呼吸的能力
The plant took away their ability to breathe air
却使他们能从海中吸取氧气
but enabled them to draw oxygen from the sea.
他们在海中定居下来
They settled in the ocean,
远离战争与疾病
away from war and diseases.
[外语]我们走
我母亲在那里生下我
My mother gave birth to me there
我成了塔洛坎出生的第一个孩子
and I became the firstborn son of talokan.
那种植物给了我脚踝上的翅膀
The plant gave me wings on my ankles
以及一对朝天耳
and ears that pointed to the clouds.
我是变种人
I was a mutant.
我能在空中游泳 老得比较慢
I could swim in the sky and age slower.
呼吸我们祖先呼吸的空气
Breathe the air our ancestors breathed.
年纪大了之后
As she grew older,
我母亲思念她曾熟悉的陆地生活
my mother mourned the life on land that she once knew...
抑郁而终
And died with a broken heart.
她要我答应将她葬在家乡的土里
She made me promise to Bury her in the soil of her homeland.
我完全没料到会在那里发现什么
Nothing could prepare me for what I found there.
[外语]这是谁的孩子
[外语]射击
[外语]发射
[外语]你是魔鬼
[外语]撒旦之子
一个西班牙教士咒骂我
A Spanish man of faith cursed me.
死在我的手下之前
As he died by my hand,
他称呼我…
he called me...
[外语]你是个缺少爱的孩子
[外语]缺少爱的孩子
缺少爱的孩子
The child without love.
我的名字就是这么来的
And I took my name from there.
纳摩
"Namor."
因为我对陆地没有爱
Because I have no love for the surface world.
你跟我说这些做什么
Why are you telling me all of this?
让你明白我为何得杀那个科学家
So that you can understand why I have to kill the scientist.
要是我们带她去瓦坎达呢
What if we took her to wakanda?
放了我们
Let us go.
我向你保证
I give you my word.
她会待在我国
She will remain in my country.
我不能冒险 公主
I cannot risk that, Princess.
那就把我留下来
Then keep me instead.
我想看看你的国家
I'd love to see your nation.
你不能这副模样下去
Well, you can't go down there in that.
你几乎立刻就会失温
Hypothermia will grip you almost instantaneously.
你的血液会有毒
Your blood will become toxic
海洋的压力会压碎你每根骨头
and the pressure of the ocean will break every bone in your body.
但也能穿潜水装
Or you can wear a suit.
我们有几件 过来
We have some of them. Come on.
跟紧
Stay close.
喂 纳摩 等等
Hey! Namor, wait!
(塔洛坎 首都)
你好
Hello.
好美
It's beautiful.
它是振金制成的
It's made of vibranium.
对
Yes.
在海洋深处
In the depths of the ocean,
我将阳光带给我的人民
I brought the sun to my people.
我知道你希望我饶了那科学家一命
I know you wished me to spare the life of the scientist.
现在你知道我得保护什么了
But now you see what I have to protect.
娜奇雅 你的直觉没错
Nakia, your hunch was correct.
我侦测到苏睿基莫由耳环的位置
I have picked up a location on shuri's kimoyo earrings.
讯号来自一座水底洞穴
The signal is coming from an unden/vater cavern
在海面下约140米
approximately 140 meters below the surface.
王后 我发现她的讯号
Queen mother, I've found her signal.
来自一座水底洞穴
It's coming from an underwater cave.
如果她在那里 我一定会遭到阻力
If she's down there, I'm sure I'll encounter resistance.
你要我如何进行
How would you like me to proceed?
不计代价救回公主
Retrieve the Princess by any means necessary.
我会设法引诱纳摩出来
I will attempt to draw namor out.
你是第一个从陆上来到塔洛坎的人
You are the first person from the surface to come to talokan.
请收下这代表我们谢意的纪念品
Please take this as a token of our gratitude.
它用拯救塔洛坎的植物制作
It was made with the plant that saved talokan.
你还年轻 公主
You are young, Princess.
等你到我这年纪 就会明白
When you age as I do, you realize
我们都会失去每个心爱的人
we all lose everyone we love.
但失去我哥时
But when I lost my brother,
感觉不一样
it just felt different.
他默默受苦
He suffered in silence.
最后他向我求助时 我却帮不上忙
When he finally asked me to help him, I couldn't.
这是什么道理…
How does that make sense
祖先赋予我天赋与能力
that the ancestors would give me gifts and skills
拯救我哥 我却没办法
to help me save my brother, and I couldn't?
这个问题我没有答案
I don't have an answer for that question.
我的祖先常说
My ancestors would often say,
受过最大苦难者才能成为伟大领袖
"only the most broken people can be great leaders."
我很佩服你在这里的建设
I admire what you have built here.
以及你用心保护人民
And how you've protected your people.
但身为瓦坎达公主
But as Princess of wakanda,
我不能容忍你杀害那个小女生
I will not stand for you killing that young woman.
除非我回去 我的国家不会善罢干休
My nation will not rest until I'm returned.
没有她我不会离开
I'm not leaving without her.
我们必须找到和平解决的方法
We need to find a peaceful way to resolve this.
重点已经不是那个科学家
It is no longer about the scientist.
几百年来
For centuries,
陆上国家征服奴役我们这种民族
the surface nations have conquered and enslaved people like us.
为了争夺资源
Over resources.
从埋葬母亲的那天起
Since the day I buried my mother,
我就让人民准备面对他们来犯
I have prepared my people for the time they will come for us.
那台机器代表时候到了
And that machine is the sign that the time is now.
我必须知道瓦坎达是敌是友
I need to know if wakanda is an ally or an enemy.
没有灰色地带
There is no in-between.
所以你打算对全世界开战
So you plan to wage war on the entire world,
还希望瓦坎达帮你
and you want wakanda to help you?
太离谱了
That's madness.
任何国家有机会都想掠夺瓦坎达
There isn't a nation that wouldn't plunder wakanda if given a chance.
如果我们结盟
If we make an alliance,
就能先发制人 保护彼此
we can protect each other by striking them first.
等摆脱那些国家的威胁后
Then, when the threat of these nations has been eliminated,
那个科学家就能回到瓦坎达
the scientist will be returned to wakanda.
如果瓦坎达不接受呢
And if wakanda does not accept, what then?
科学家难逃一死
The scientist will die.
瓦坎达将是第一个瓦解的国家
And wakanda will be the first nation to fall.
攻击我的人民
An attack on my people?
对
Yes.
我要你听我说
And I want you to listen to me.
瓦坎达打不赢塔洛坎
Wakanda cannot win a war with talokan.
[外语]有人召唤您
[外语]库库尔坎
那晚我听到你和你母亲在河边的对话
I heard you that night, with your mother at the river.
你说你想烧光这个世界
You said you wanted to burn the world.
让我们一起烧吧
Let us burn it together.
拉玛达王后不肯卖振金给我们
Queen ramonda
他们绑架建造机器的小女生
And now they abducted a young woman who built the machine.
恕我直言 莉莉威廉斯是天才少女
Yeah, with all due respect, riri Williams is a child prodigy
比她麻省理工学院的教授更厉害
who was running circles around all of her professors.
瓦坎达人招募她加入他们的交流计划
The wakandans were recruiting her as part of their outreach program.
如此而已
Nothing more.
你们却趁夜黑风高派特种部队
And then, you guys send in a SWAT team under cover of night
逮捕一个国际强权的女王储
to arrest the crown Princess of an international superpower.
总统想对瓦坎达采取攻势
The president wants to take offensive action against wakanda.
哪种攻势
What type of offensive action?
暗中颠覆
Destabilization.
罗斯探员是我们的专家
Well, special officer Ross is our expert.
那 罗斯 你有何看法
So, Ross, what do you think?
我的消息来源指出祸首另有其人
My sources are telling me that there's someone else out there.
- 另一个国家 - 有可能 我不知道
- Another nation? - Could be. I don't know.
你们得给我时间好好调查
You've gotta give me enough time to investigate this properly,
否则我们到时候的交战对手
otherwise we're gonna find ourselves at war
会是一个军事实力
with a country whose military capacity
超乎想象的国家
we can't even comprehend.
局长
Director?
我认为他是专家
I think he's the expert.
我想攻击瓦坎达并不明智
I think it would be a mistake to attack wakanda.
喂
Yes?
我们碰上问题了
We have a problem.
(佛得角 库拉维洛)
我的女儿还活着吗
Is my daughter alive?
公主安然无恙
The Princess is alive and well.
她自己要求前往塔洛坎
She requested to be taken to talokan.
目前她会留在那里
She will remain there for the time being.
我能用什么把她换回来
What can I offer you in exchange?
不能
Nothing.
恕我不认同
I beg to differ.
你们攻击美国人的开采船
The Americans are preparing to blame wakanda
他们准备怪到瓦坎达头上
for your attack on their mining ship.
让我的女儿和科学家回来
Return my daughter and the scientist
否则我就告诉他们有你们这个国度
or I will inform them of your existence.
如果你泄漏给美国人
If you tell the Americans about us,
如果你设法找我们
if you try to find us,
或者我在海上发现瓦坎达的船只
or if I discover a single wakandan ship in the ocean,
我就杀了公主
I will kill the Princess.
我也会到瓦坎达
I will come to wakanda
亲手杀了你
and iwill kill you.
怎么了
So, what happened?
他想对陆上国家开战
He wants to go to war with the surface world,
还要我帮他
and asked me to help him.
我必须想想看
I need to think.
我们别想离开了
We ain't never gettin' out of here.
[外语]把矛放下
[外语]杀了公主
[外语]刀子放下
[外语]你…
[外语]你杀了她
[外语]放她走
[外语]你就不必死
苏睿
Shuri...
[外语]左手臂移开
你还好吗
Are you okay?
- 珠子给我 - 我们走
- Give me your beads! - Let's go.
- 珠子给我 我能救她 - 我们快走
- Give me your beads. I can save her. - We have to go.
苏睿 我不认识她 但我们得听她的
Shuri, I don't know who this lady is, but we need to listen to her.
我用声波攻击她
Listen, I hit her with a Sonic round.
近距离绝对致命 她活不了的
It is lethal from this distance. There is no chance.
你不懂 这会引发战争
You don't understand. This will mean war.
- 我们该走了 - 等等
- We have to go. - Wait!
他们有对你怎样吗
Did they hurt you?
没有
No. No.
谢谢你
Thank you.
[外语]不客气
- 葛里奥 - 是 王后
- griot. - Yes, my queen.
立刻带我们回瓦坎达
Return us to wakanda at once.
[外语]我的孩子怎么了
[外语]瓦坎达人
[外语]他们来救她
[外语]库库尔坎
[外语]你能救我吗
[外语]她死了吗
[外语]对
[外语]安息吧 孩子
[外语]他们趁着…
[外语]你跟王后谈话的时候跑来
[外语]我们不该信任她的
[外语]公主见过我们家
[外语]有什么能阻止他们
[外语]攻击塔洛坎
[外语]我会阻止
[外语]塔洛坎奋起
[外语]为了寻求合作伙伴
[外语]我一时不查
[外语]失去判断力
[外语]同时…
[外语]我连累了
[外语]我们大家
[外语]塔洛坎
[外语]绝对不再
[外语]有所动摇
[外语]纳摩菈
[外语]阿杜玛
[外语]等我们复仇成功
[外语]他们就再也不敢
[外语]越雷池一步
[外语]接近塔洛坎
[外语]塔洛坎奋起
公主 幸好您回来了
Princess, it is good to have you back.
您离开后首都气氛紧张
The city has been on edge since you left.
强化各水道的声波障碍
Fortify the Sonic barriers for all waterways.
公主
Princess?
安妮卡
Neka.
感谢祖先保佑
Thank the ancestors. Hmm?
我想还你这些
I just wanted to return these.
不 留着
No. Keep them.
可能很快会用上
Might need them soon.
您在那边拿的吗
Did you get that from down there?
您真的见到一个水中帝国
Is it true you saw an underwater empire?
对
Hmm.
那里很美
It is beautiful.
但那些人很危险 安妮卡
But these people are dangerous, Aneka.
所以 莉莉威廉斯小姐
So, miss riri Williams,
你觉得瓦坎达怎么样
what do you think of wakanda?
那些故事根本是轻描淡写
The stories just don't do this place justice.
非常棒
It's great.
但我真的很想回家
But I really would like to go home.
你需要耐心一点
You will need to be patient.
我至少能打给我妈吧
Can I at least call my mom?
战犬娜奇雅已经将公主送回家了
The Princess has been brought home by the war dog nakia.
荣耀哈努曼
Glory to hanuman.
那个特务又救了瓦坎达一次
Mm. The spy saves wakanda once again.
相信女王会赏她
The queen will reward her
终生流放
with lifetime banishment. I'm sure of it.
奥克耶
Okoye.
[外语]谢谢你 妹妹
萨诺斯攻击过后
After Thanos' attack,
你不告而别
when you left without saying a word,
让人很伤心
it hurt.
我很后悔没在你们身边
I regret not being there with all of you.
那并不好受
It was not easy.
他是…
He was...
大家的国王和黑豹
King and black panther to everyone.
但对我来说
But to me...
他就是一切
He was everything.
我的帝查拉
My t'challa.
他说走就走 我…
When he was taken away from me, just like that, I...
我必须离开
I had to step away
让自己好好伤心一阵子
and let myself break.
我不能…
I couldn't just...
像没事一样继续过日子
Keep going as if nothing had happened, you know.
我们遭受攻击
We are under attack.
拿着
Here.
[外语]救这个
你还好吗 没事吧
Are you okay? Are you all right?
葛里奥 启动日鸟号
Griot, activate the sunbird.
苏睿 你在哪
Shuri, where are you?
正要赶去市区
Making my way to the city right now.
不准去 这是命令
Stand down! That is an order!
母后 我和安妮卡能提供空中支援
Mother, I'm with Aneka. We can provide air support.
- 安妮卡 别让她离开 - 讯号有问题
- Aneka, do not let her leave the lab. - Mother, you're... You're breaking up.
我们听不见 苏睿
Shuri!
我爱你 掰
Love you. Bye!
你挂掉王后的电话
You just hung up on the queen.
我挂掉我妈的电话
I just hung up on my mom.
不一样 走吧
There's a difference. Come. Let's go!
有人入侵
Invaders!
妈妈…
Mama! Mama!
[外语]回去 调头
急救员受到一种声波催眠影响
Emts are suffering a form of Sonic hypnosis.
[外语]接住孩子
将军 塞住耳朵
General, plug your ears.
是 王后
Yes, my queen.
我能帮忙吗
Can I help?
快过来
Come, quickly.
[外语]战士
双臂交叉
Cross your arms...
[外语]孩子
娜奇雅
Nakia.
[外语]是
[外语]我们会找到你妈妈的
鱼人
The fish man.
[外语]护卫人员已被引出王宫
[外语]现在就看您的决定
[外语]求救
可恶 他太快了
Shit, he's too fast.
他在水中更快
He's even faster in the water.
启动系统超控
Activating system override.
- 不 等等 我来修理 - 不能丢下你
- NO! Wait! I'll fix it. - Can't leave you here, shuri!
看到她了吗
Do you see her?
有 在那边
Yes. Right there.
快走 孩子
Go, child.
什么 把你留在这里
Wait, what? And leave you here?
快跑
Run!
奥克耶 快出发
Okoye, move now!
[外语]救那个孩子
是她造成的
She did this.
一周后
In one week's time,
我会带大军回来
I will return with my entire army
你们加入我们 对抗陆上世界
and you will join us against the surface world,
否则我就让瓦坎达从地表消失
or I will wash wakanda from the face of the earth.
[外语]加油 王后
母后
Mother.
- 别让她过来 - 母后
- Keep her back! - Mother!
- 妈妈… - 埋葬亡者
- Mama! Mama! - Bury your dead.
哀悼至亲
Mourn your losses.
你现在是女王了
You are queen now.
母后
Mother!
放开我 母后
Get off of me! Mother!
妈妈
Mama!
母后
Mother!
[外语]醒醒 王后
[外语]让我看看
[外语]醒过来
帮帮我
Help me!
妈妈
Mama!
[外语]醒来 王后
[外语]她去世了
妈妈
Mama!
贾巴里地民众请你节哀
Jabariland offers you their comfort for your loss.
你必须…
You must mourn her
依照祖传的仪式来悼念她
in accordance to the rituals of your ancestors.
别埋首于你的科技
Do not Bury yourself in your technology.
你来做什么
Why are you here?
我答应过你哥
I promised your brother
我会给你建议
that I would provide you with counsel
以及保护
and protection.
但今天我需要你的意见
But I am in need of your advice today.
你们的长老向我提议一件事
Your tribal elders have approached me with a proposition.
他们希望撤离首都 在贾巴里地…
They wish to evacuate the city and set up camp
暂时安顿下来
in jabariland.
现在你想听一个不屑传统的孩子
So, now you are keen to hear from a child
发表意见
who scoffs at tradition?
这个世界
The world...
这个世界对你太残酷了
The world has taken too much from you
毕竟你还是个孩子
for you to still be considered a child.
我们想知道的是
It is in my people's interest to know
你有什么想法
which way your mind is leaning.
长老陷入绝望
The elders are desperate.
首都脆弱不堪
The city is vulnerable.
如果你提供他们生活所需
If you are to provide for them,
他们会万分感激
they will be in great debt to you.
你的心呢
And what of your heart?
你的心怎么想
Which way is your heart leaning?
我刚埋葬了最后一个了解我的人
I just buried the last person who truly knew me.
我的心跟着她入土了
My heart was buried with her.
天啊
Oh, man.
你的橄榄油快坏掉了
Yeah, your olive oil's about to go bad.
你来做什么
What... what are you doing here?
我肚子饿 还有…
I'm hungry. And...
一场悲剧震撼国际社会
Tragedy strikes the international community.
拉玛达王后 卢蒙巴之女惊传死讯
Sources can now confirm that queen ramonda, daughter of lumumba, has died.
西方盟友表示原因可能是内战…
Western allies say that civil conflict was the likely cause of the queen's...
你有什么看法吗
You have any comment?
不晓得你的朋友还瞒着你什么
I wonder what else your friends are keeping from you.
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
我跟瓦坎达王国私下没联系
I have no unsanctioned contact with the kingdom of wakanda.
那些珠子呢
What about the beads?
什么
What?
珠子
The beads.
在你抵达那里之前
I had them bugged
我在上面装了窃听器
before you ever even got there.
我听过你每次对话
I've been privy to every conversation you've had,
包括那通与王后的叛国电话
including that treasonous call with the queen.
愿她安息
May she rest in peace.
但那是好事
But it's good.
对我们来说
Well, for us.
你知道吗 瓦坎达人救过我
All right. You know what? The wakandans saved my life.
他们是好人
They're a good people.
你可曾想过
You ever thought for a second
他们可能怎么做
what they could be doing?
你想过我们会怎么做吗
Ever thought what we would be doing
如果美国是唯一有振金的国家
if the us was the only country in the world with vibranium?
我还真的幻想过
Oh, I actually dream about that.
小瓦 拜托
Val. Val, please.
叫我德芳亭局长
It's director de fontaine.
你母亲保护我 把我当成自己小孩
Your mother protected me like I was one of her own.
我至少能回报她
The least that I could do is try to return the favor.
我们得设法削弱纳摩的威力
We need to find a way to weaken namor.
即便如此 他还是个问题
Even weakened, he's still gonna be a problem.
黑豹保护瓦坎达从未失败
The black panther has never failed to protect wakanda.
我以为黑豹走了
I thought the black panther was gone.
我哥死了
My brother is dead.
不代表没有黑豹
But it doesn't mean the black panther is gone.
葛里奥
Griot?
我们先进行比较分析
Let's start by running a comparative analysis
比较制造合成心型药草
between our attempts at creating a synthetic heart-shaped herb...
以及这手环的纤维
And the fibers from this bracelet.
是 公主
Yes, Princess.
既然这从富含振金的土壤长出来
Since this was grown from vibranium-rich soil,
可能具有我们能利用的类似特点
they may share some base-level similarities that we can exploit.
遵命 公主
As you wish, Princess.
麻烦也上传我哥的DNA
Please upload my brother's DNA also.
上传中
Uploading now.
他怎么长得跟他们不同
why doesn't he look like them?
他的生理构造截然不同
His physiology is completely different.
他们不能飞也没有尖耳朵
None of them fly or have pointed ears like him.
看守我们的女人嘴上和脖子上
The women that were guarding us, they had water over their mouths
都有水
and on their necks.
他却没有
He didn't have that.
有几种动物不需鳃从水中汲取氧气
Several organisms don't need gills to extract oxygen from the water, so...
就像水母
It's like a jellyfish.
他从皮肤吸收氧气
He just absorbs the oxygen from his skin.
- 这过程叫扩散 - 扩散
- It's a process called diffusion. - Diffusion.
只要一天没选出统治者
every day that passes without selecting the ruler
就浪费一天
is a day wasted.
我们得在纳摩带战士回来前处理掉他
We must deal with namor before he brings his warriors back here.
如何处理威力那么强大的人
And how are we to deal with a man with that much power?
在击落你的飞机前
In that attack, before he took out your plane,
他跳回水中
he jumped back into the water.
要是那让他更强大呢
What if that's what makes him strong?
他从皮肤上的水吸入氧气
He's breathing air and getting oxygen from the water on his skin.
如果让他干掉 他就不会那么强
If we could find a way to dry his ass out, he won't be as strong.
这办法好
Yo, that's it.
葛里奥
Griot.
把皇家鹰爪战斗机变成渗透蒸发舱
We need to convert the royal Talon fighter into a pervaporation chamber.
有可能吗
Is that even possible?
有
Yes.
你得帮我们设计他
You're going to help us trap him.
请带威廉斯小姐去工作地点
Please show miss Williams where she's working.
这边请
Right this way.
你几岁建造第一台机器
How old were you when you built your first machine?
三岁
Three.
我继父是汽车技工 他想造飞机
My stepdad was a car mechanic. He wanted to build airplanes.
他给我工具 让我自己玩
He gave me these tools and let me just work it out.
这些都是谁教你的
So who taught you how to do all that you do?
我大哥
My big brother.
我曾是瓦坎达军队最危险的战士
I was the tip of the spear of wakanda's army.
这可不是我的风格
This is not me.
何况我现在是一介平民
Besides, I'm a civilian now.
我缴回了武器
I turned in my weapon.
我也为你打造了新矛
I built you a new spear as well.
新的
A new one?
对
Yes.
这鬼玩意叫什么
What is this contraption's name anyway?
午夜天使
The midnight angel.
Midnight angel?
[外语]听我说
这能让我们与他们势均力敌
This will even the odds against them.
姐姐 我要你随时待命
Sister, I need you to be ready when I call you.
求求你
Please.
苏睿
shuri.
是
Yes.
你做了几套
How many of these did you make?
我去贾巴里前哨站找过你
I looked for you at the Jabari outpost.
谁都不能逼我离开家
I won't be forced out of my home.
你真的很叛逆
You have such a rebellious spirit.
你为什么加入朵拉亲卫队
Why did you join the dora?
你何必在乎
Why do you care?
我依然很想为国而战
I still have a lot of fight left in me.
告诉我 安妮卡 凯亚娜之女
Tell me, Aneka, daughter of kyana,
你心中还有为国而战的斗志吗
do you still have some fight left in you?
你有什么打算
What do you have in mind?
葛里奥
griot,
信赖率多少
what's the confidence rate?
98.7% 公主
98.7%, Princess.
您要我打印心型药草吗
Would you like me to print the heart-shaped herb?
[外语]嗨 苏睿
我以为你回海地了
Thought you'd be back in Haiti by now.
我还是瓦坎达人
I'm still wakandan, you know.
你最近都在忙这个
This is what you've been up to.
是
Yes.
这个东西
What you have here, now,
是恢复瓦坎达守护者的机会
is a chance to restore wakanda's protector.
它会是巴圣加发现心型药草以来
It would be the greatest gift
最伟大的赠礼
since bashenga's discovery.
很快就知道了 过来
We'll soon find out. Come.
- 葛里奥 - 是 公主
- Griot? - Yes, Princess.
打印
Print it.
怎么知道有没有用
How will we know if it works?
如果它会发光的话
If it glows.
[外语]你成功了
我们不该烧香之类的吗
I mean, shouldn't we be burning incense or something?
只有巴斯蒂知道祖先如何来到实验室
Only bast knows how the ancestors will make it to this lab.
你确定不要我埋葬你
Are you sure you don't want me to Bury you?
我要你能触及我的胸部
Need you to have access to my chest,
以防我心跳停止
just in case I go through cardiac arrest.
心跳停止
"Cardiac arrest"?
她开玩笑的
She's joking,
对吧
right?
Right?
容许这心型药草
Allow this heart-shaped herb
赋予你黑豹的力量
to give you the strength of the black panther
带你前往祖先之地
and take you to the ancestral plane.
[外语]拉玛达
[外语]我们恳求您来到女儿身边
母后
Mother?
恩贾达卡
N'jadaka.
小堂妹
Lil' cousin.
怎么会
How?
方法不如原因重要吧
How is never as important as why, right?
你选择了我
You chose me.
不可能 我绝不会选你
Impossible. I would never choose you.
你为何服下药草
Why did you take the herb?
为了见家人
To see my family.
鬼扯
No, that's bullshit.
你不相信祖先之地是真的
You didn't believe the ancestral plane was real, did you?
那为什么服下它
So, why did you take it, then?
你不必骗我
You don't have to lie to me.
我想更强大
So I can be strong.
强大要做什么
Strong to do what?
看吧
See?
我们比你想的更相像
We're more alike than you think.
我服用它也是要为祖先报仇
I took it to avenge my ancestors too.
我跟你完全不一样
I'm nothing like you.
你是为了自己
You took it for yourself,
然后毁掉剩下的药草
then destroyed the rest.
胜之不武的国王
Unworthy king,
害怕被取代
afraid of being replaced.
只是个懦夫
Just a coward.
我壮士断腕 改变瓦坎达
I had the courage to do what was necessary to change wakanda.
在我登基前
How many people like your scientist
瓦坎达保护了几个科学家那种人
did wakanda protect before I took the throne?
懦夫…
Cowards.
就是在我之前的那些黑豹
That was the panthers that came before me,
在帝查拉之前
and before t'challa.
别提到我哥
Don't mention my brother.
他是因为你才死的
You're the reason why he's dead.
你烧毁药草 害我们失去守护者
You burnt the herb, left us with no protector.
然后纳摩进攻 杀了母后
Then namor struck and killed my mother.
你的手上沾满他们的血
Their blood is on your hands.
不能算在我头上
That ain't on me.
你不准…
And don't you dare
藐视你母亲的牺牲
take that away from your mother.
她牺牲自己 保护那失落部落的女孩
She sacrificed her life to protect a young girl from the lost tribe.
你父亲是伪君子
Your father, he was a hypocrite.
他也会杀了那女孩
He would've killed that girl.
他就杀了自己的弟弟
Shit, he killed his own brother.
帝查拉太高尚了
T'challa was too noble.
他让杀父凶手活命
He let the man who murdered your father live.
而你站在这里
And here you stand.
你要像你哥一样高尚
Are you gonna be noble like your brother
还是像我一样
or take care of business...
解决问题
Like me?
你还好吗
Are you okay?
你见到谁
Who did you see?
没有
No one.
[外语]怎么回事
我失败了
I failed.
没成功
It didn't work.
苏睿
Hey, shuri.
他们抛弃我
They abandoned me.
他们绝对不会那样
They would never do that.
我做了所有该做的事
I did everything I was supposed to do.
重制药草
I re-created the herb.
我做了那蠢仪式 为了什么
I just did your stupid ritual, and for what?
- 别激动 - 他们为何不来找我
- Relax. - Why didn't they come for me?
别激动
Just relax.
天啊
Shit.
我也能服用吗
Can I get some of that too?
我想…
I think...
你需要一套战服
You're going to need a suit.
有更多人会从首都来
There are more people coming from the city.
他们需要更多空间
They need more space.
那又怎样
So what?
你们是访客
You are visitors.
你们能完成任何事就是奇迹了
It is a wonder how anything gets done with you people.
公主
The Princess!
她成功了
She has done it!
黑豹不死
The black panther lives!
纳摩认为瓦坎达不堪一击
Namor believes wakanda is on her knees.
我们的王后遭杀害
Our queen murdered.
首都毁损
Our capital destroyed.
他相信我们没有守护者
He believes we have no protector.
但现在…
But now...
现在是反击的时候
Now is our time to strike.
怎么反击 我们根本找不到他
How, when we don't even know how to find him?
我们让纳摩自己送上门
We'll bring namor to us.
- 又来这里 - 不是
- Here, again? - No.
海上的一个偏远地点
A distant location at sea.
好
All right.
就算这样行得通
Let's say this does work.
假设我们能杀了他
Hmm. Assuming we can kill this man
他会飞 可能壮如浩克
who can fly and is potentially as strong as the hulk...
杀死他就是解决之道吗
Is murdering him the right solution?
你要他的项上人头
You were calling for his head
他的罪不过是恐吓而已
when his only crime was intimidation.
是什么变了 恩巴库大王
What has changed, lord m'Baku?
他的士兵…
His soldiers
并未称呼他将军或国王
did not call him general or king.
他们叫他库库尔坎
They called him k'UK'ulkan.
那是什么
What is that?
羽蛇神
The feather serpent god.
怎样
What?
你们以为我们住在山上
Do you think because we are living in the mountains,
就没书可看吗
we do not have access to books?
各位长老
Elders,
如果你们允许
with your permission,
我想单独跟恩巴库大王谈谈
I would like to talk with lord m'Baku alone.
[外语]好
纳摩还不会松手
Namor's not finished.
他誓言摧毁陆地世界
He promised to destroy the surface world.
现在是我们杀他的机会
Now is our opportunity to take him.
- 你在怕什么 - 战争
- What are you afraid of? - War.
如果纳摩真是他人民心中的神
If namor is indeed a god to his people,
杀了他可能引发永恒之战
killing him will risk eternal war.
那又如何
And so what?
我母后的命不值得永恒之战吗
Was my mother's life not worth eternal war?
当然值得
Of course it was.
她当然值得
Of course she was.
但她不会希望你那么做
But it is not what she would have wanted for you.
那也不是我…
And it is not what I want...
要给我人民的
For my people.
你说得好像母后还在
You speak of my mother as if she's still here.
说她希望我如何
Of what she would've wanted for me.
她的希望和梦想
Her hopes and her dreams.
但她死了
But she's dead.
她走了
She's gone!
纳摩淹死她 就在我眼前
Namor drowned her, right in front of me!
她的梦想
So, her dreams,
她的目标 对我的期望
her goals, her hopes for me...
都不存在
It doesn't exist.
已经不重要了
It doesn't matter anymore.
重要的是我要什么
What matters is what I want,
我要纳摩的命
and what I want is namor dead!
你得帮我实现
And you're going to help me get it.
[外语]清楚了吗
我们一大早出发
We leave in the morning.
你好
Hi.
早
Good morning.
如果能活下来
If we survive this,
别忘了你和我在海地有个家
I want you to know you have a home with me in Haiti.
来 握住我的手
Here. Take my hands.
[外语]深呼吸
苏睿 老实对我说
Shuri, I want you to be honest with me.
你服下药草后见到谁
Who did you see when you took the herb?
如果你为了复仇而战
If you go to war for vengeance,
填补不了失去她所留下的空缺
it will not fill the hole left from her loss.
它只会变得更大
It will only grow larger,
最后会吞噬你
and it will consume you.
它已经吞噬掉我了
It already has.
[外语]库库尔坎 另一台振金探测器
[外语]已在海洋中运作
[外语]在哪里
(大西洋某处)
[外语]冲出海面
为了王后
For the queen.
莉莉 上面状况如何
Riri, how's it going up there?
葛里奥先生
Hey, Mr. Griot.
我现在需要支援
I could really use that backup right now.
我以为你不会开口
Lthought you'd never ask.
可恶
Shit.
可恶 他真快
Shit, he's fast.
但我更快
But I'm faster.
看我对付你
I got you.
看你的了 苏睿
It's on you now, shuri.
- 公主 - 不对
- Princess... - No.
我是黑豹 我是来报仇的
I am the black panther, and I'm here for retribution!
渗透蒸发舱启动
Pervaporation cells activated.
怎么了
What's wrong?
需要一杯水吗
You need a glass of water?
逮到他了
Yo, we got him.
- 太好了 - 纳摩被逮了
- Good! - Namor has been captured.
[外语]撤回
返回瓦坎达
Back to wakanda!
出发
Move out!
怎么回事
What is going on?
声波发射器被摧毁了
The Sonic emitter has been destroyed.
这下糟了
That can't be good.
黑豹 海豹号失去动力
Panther, the sea leopard has lost power,
他们死伤惨重
and they are experiencing significant casualties.
奥克耶
Okoye.
黑豹
Panther.
安妮卡
Aneka.
奥克耶
O koye!
时间到了
It is time.
为了瓦坎达
For wakanda!
瓦坎达
Wakanda!
葛里奥 受损状况如何
Griot, what's the damage?
受损惨重 他的矛以纯振金制成
Catastrophic. His spear is made of raw vibranium.
- 船随时会爆炸 - 带我们到沙漠
- The ship could explode at any second. - Get us to the desert.
不
No!
[外语]击沉船只
姐 我帮你
I got you, sis.
抓好
Hold on.
[外语]战士
[外语]你会说母语
[外语]你能用它问候祖先
放开我
Get offme!
过来
All right, come here.
[外语]你去见你的祖先吧
如果公主不快一点
May the ancestors save us
愿祖先能救我们
if the Princess does not hurry.
我们可能会去见祖先
We may be going to join them.
如果真是那样
If so, hey,
带他们通通一起去
let us take as many of them with us as we can.
原本可以不必如此
It could've been different.
[外语]我需要水
你要像你哥一样高尚
Are you gonna be noble like your brother
还是像我一样
or take care of business
解决问题
like me?
我不是我哥
I'm not my brother.
纳摩会向我求饶
Namorwill beg me for mercy
我会眼睁睁看着他死
as I stand and watch as he dies.
[外语]我就是王
瓦坎达万岁
Wakanda forever!
苏睿
Shuri.
妈妈
Mama.
让他看见…
Show him
你的本色
who you are.
投降吧
Yield,
瓦坎达会保护你们的海洋
and wakanda will protect your oceans.
我们会保守你们的秘密
We will protect your secrets.
投降吧
Yield,
你的人民就能活命
and your people will live.
复仇使我们疯狂
Vengeance has consumed us.
不能让它伤害我们的人民
We cannot let it consume our people.
[外语]我投降
[外语]塔洛坎人
[外语]我们回家吧
[外语]这场战争结束了
瓦坎达万岁
Wakanda forever!
谢谢你 我的爱
thank you, my love.
嗨
Yo.
准备回家了吗
All set to head home?
只要你确定警方不会在机场等我
As long as you're sure the police won't be waiting for me at the airport.
放心 都处理好了
Don't worry. Took care of that.
但是帮人做作业的生意最好暂缓
But you might want to slow down on your homework-for-hire business.
出包被逮到我可帮不了你
Get caught slipping, I can't help you with that.
他们说你有事跟我谈
They said you wanted to talk to me about something?
对
Yes.
你的战服 设计得很棒
Your suit. It's a great design,
但不能让你带走
but can't let you leave with it.
没关系
It's all good.
至少我能帮瓦坎达替我收拾善后
Figured the least I could do is help wakanda clean up my mess.
我还有一样东西给你看
I have one more thing to show you.
过来
Come.
花了一段时间才从河里找到所有零件
Took me a while to find all the parts from the river,
可是很值得
but it was worth it.
你怎么…
How did you...
这是我爸的车
It's my dad's car.
我们以前常改装它
We used to work on it before...
- 你确定是这辆 - 整台都是
- you sure this is her? - Every part.
我会把它运到波士顿
Have it shipped to Boston.
它会比你先到
Be there before you arrive.
抱一下
Bring it in, man.
黑豹 威廉斯小姐的座驾到了
Panther, miss Williams' transport has arrived.
好好保重
Look after yourself.
你确定不去芝加哥
Sure you're not trying to slide to Chicago?
看场公牛队比赛
Catch a bulls game?
应该很有趣 但我有事要处理
Sounds fun, but I have something I need to take care of.
现在让我们欢迎
And now I present to you
苏睿公主
Princess shuri,
黑豹
the black panther!
黑豹向各位问好
The black panther sends her regards,
但她今天无法到场
but she will not be joining us today.
我 恩巴库
I, m'Baku,
贾巴里部落领袖
leader of the Jabari tribe,
瓦坎达之子
son of wakanda,
希望挑战…
wish to challenge
王位
for the throne.
[外语]你有什么心事 孩子
[外语]我一辈子渴望与您并肩作战
[外语]想到您向瓦坎达人屈服…
[外语]黑豹大可杀了我
[外语]你想她为什么没动手
[外语]黑豹是陆上第一强国…
[外语]权力最强大的人
[外语]但她没有盟友
[外语]现在她同情塔洛坎人
[外语]有了这个盟友
[外语]塔洛坎将比以往更强大
[外语]陆上世界将进攻瓦坎达
[外语]瓦坎达会向我们求援
[外语]相信我
那是什么
What the hell is this?
我们能调头吗
Can we turn around?
不晓得 那会浪费一小时
I don't know, man. We'll lose an hour.
过去看一下吧
Why don't you go check it out?
好
Okay.
我是萧佛
Yeah, this is shauver.
有棵树挡住去路
Yeah, looks like we got a tree blocking our way.
我们该怎么处理
How do you want us to proceed?
什么…
What the...
殖民者被链住了
A colonizer in chains.
大开眼界
Now I have seen everything.
真好笑
Funny.
[外语]我们走
[外语]谢谢
[外语]不客气
嗨
Hey.
[外语]欢迎
真高兴见到你
It's good to see you.
都准备好了
Everything is ready.
等我一下
Just give me one moment, eh?
其实…
Actually,
我想我该自己来
I think I should do it on my own.
没问题
Of course.
《黑豹2：瓦坎达万岁》
苏睿
Shuri,
我们能加入吗
can we join you now?
这是我儿子 杜桑
This is my son, toussaint.
杜桑
Toussaint,
这是你姑姑苏睿
this is your aunty, shuri.
嗨
Hi.
我们认为他在这里长大比较好
We agreed it was better for him to grow up here.
远离继位的压力
Away from the pressure of the throne.
你父亲…
Your father,
你的爸爸
your baba,
让我们准备好接受他离世 对吧
prepared us for his death, didn't he?
但他不要我们参加葬礼
But he didn't want us to go to the funeral
他觉得时机还不适合
because he felt the time was not yet right.
我们自己在这里为他办了仪式
So we had our own ceremony for him here.
母后见过他吗
Did my mother meet him?
见过
She did.
很高兴见到你
It's nice to meet you.
杜桑这名字真好
Toussaint is a beautiful name.
蕴含了一段伟大的历史
It holds a great history.
谢谢 你的名字也很酷
Thanks. Yours is cool, too, I guess.
我妈说你很会保守秘密
My mom says you are good at keeping secrets.
真的吗
Is that true?
对 我能保守秘密
Yes, I can keep a good secret.
杜桑是我的海地名字
Toussaint is my Haitian name.
[外语]你是谁
我叫帝查拉王子
My name is prince t'challa,
帝查拉国王之子
son of king t'challa.
[谨以此片献给我们的挚友查德威克·鲍斯曼]
黑豹将再度回归